Register of the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 89, Communist Party of the Soviet Union on Trial records, 1919-1992; 24 reels (Reel 1.989-1.1012)
  - Opis 45
    - Memorandum (translated into Russian) to the Presidium of the TsK KPSS and to N. Khrushchev, First Secretary of the TsK KPSS, from I. Kovács analyzing the course of events that led to the counterrevolution in Hungary, denouncing the policy of the current leadership of the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party, and requesting KPSS assistance in returning to Hungary Hungarian communists forced to stay in the Soviet Union by J. Kádár, 1957 January 10 (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 64)
    - Message (sent via high frequency line) to I. Zamchevskii, Chief of the 5th European Department of the USSR Ministry of Foreign Affairs, from IU. Andropov, Soviet Ambassador to Hungary, submitting the text of a declaration on the main principles of the state, on the social and economic system of Hungary, and prospects for its political development, delivered to the Soviet Embassy by I. Bibo, member of the Executive Committee of the Petöfi Party, and approved by the Petöfi Party (National Peasant Party), the Social Democratic Party, the Peasants' Union, the Revolutionary Council of Hungarian Professionals, and the Union of Hungarian Writers, 1957 January 11 (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 65)
    - Extract from the diary of I. Zamchevskii, Chief of the 5th European Department of the USSR Ministry of Foreign Affairs, re his conversation with J. Boldoczky, Hungarian Ambassador to the Soviet Union, on February 16, 1957, about Boldoczky's impressions after a ten-day trip to Hungary, 1957 February 22 (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 66)
    - Memorandum (translated into Russian) to N. Khrushchev, First Secretary of the TsK KPSS, from M. Rákosi noting some improvement in the economic and political situation in Hungary, the slow increase in number and influence of the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party (HSWP), denouncing some of the leaders of the Hungarian government, criticizing the promotion of specialists of Jewish origin to the apparatus of the HSWP, and recommending efforts to attract to the HSWP old party cadres from internal and external exile, 1957 February 15 (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 67)
    - Memorandum (translated into Russian) to the TsK KPSS Presidium from E. Gerö, J. Revai, A. Hegedüs, and I. Kovács criticizing the leadership of the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party for its position in 1944-1956, for determining erroneous reasons for the counterrevolutionary events of 1956, for allowing the spread of revisionist opinions in the media and social and educational institutions, and for their cadres' policy; first page of the memorandum (in Hungarian), 1957 February 22; 1957 February 25 (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 68)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium re a ciphered telegram [to the TsK KPSS] from A. Yepishev; the ciphered telegram re the visit of E. Bodnarôs to the Soviet Embassy in Romania with a proposal to the Hungarian government to prepare the trial of I. Nagy and his group while they are in Romania, 1957 February-March (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 69)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium approving resolutions of the TsK KPSS re the request of the Central Committee of the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party about M. Rákosi, E. Gerö, and other Hungarian comrades staying in the Soviet Union and re Rákosi's letter of March 25, 1957; resolution of the TsK KPSS supporting the decision of the Central Committee of the HSWP banning the return of M. Rákosi and E. Gerö to Hungary for five years and the return of A. Hegedüs and others for one year; resolution of the TsK KPSS denouncing M. Rákosi's position on the situation in Hungary, on KPSS policy in Hungary, and on his own mistakes, and commissioning the TsK KPSS Secretariat to find a place of residence and a job for M. Rákosi in some part of the Soviet Union, 1957 April 18 (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 70)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium disapproving the dispatch of a telegram to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary and requesting that D. Shepilov, Minister of Foreign Affairs, talk with the Soviet ambassador to Hungary; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from Shepilov and IU. Andropov submitting the proposal of A. Kethly, leader of the Hungarian social democrats abroad, to legalize the Social Democratic Party and proposing that Hungarian friends contact A. Kethly in order to oppose her actions; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft instructions to the Soviet Ambassador to Hungary, 1957 May (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 71)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium re the arrival of J. Kádár and B. Biszku in Moscow for consultations; two directives to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary (differently formatted); memorandum to N. Khrushchev (from an unidentified official, first page only) re the agenda of Kádár's consultations with the TsK KPSS; statement on the Kádár visit to Moscow; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; comments on the Code of the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party, signed by IU. Andropov, Chief of the Department for Liaison with Communist and Workers' Parties of Socialist Countries, 1957 June (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 72)
    - Extract from the diary of L. Ilichev, Chief of the Press Department of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, re his conversation with B., Hungarian writer, re the situation in Hungary and re the joint production of the Rhapsody of Carpathia feature film based on the Illyés novel, 1957 July (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 73)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, R. Rudenko, and P. Ivashutin re their conversation with B. Biszku, Minister of Internal Affairs of Hungary, about the trial of I. Nagy and his group and about the resolutions of the Politburo of the Central Committee of the Hungarian Socialist Worker' Party, 1957 August (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 74)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chief of the Department for Liaison with Communist and Workers' Parties of Socialist Countries, re his conversation with B. Biszku,Minister of Internal Affairs of Hungary, about rescheduling the court trial of I. Nagy and his group to December 1957 or January 1958, because of the Conference of Representatives of Communist and Workers' Parties, scheduled for November 1957, the 7th Congress of Communists of Yugoslavia, and the celebration of the 40th anniversary of the October revolution, 1957 August (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 75)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium charging the TsK KPSS Secretariat with the task of considering the matters raised in a conversation between V. Baikov, Councilor of the Soviet Embassy in Hungary, and S. József, Chief of the Department of Party and Mass Organizations of the Central Committee of the Hungarian Social Workers' Party, on September 16, 1957, about internal events and the economic situation in Hungary; extract from Baikov's diary, re the conversation, 1957 September-October (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 76)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium approving draft instructions to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary with respect to a note from Yugoslavia; the instructions to be transmitted to E. Sik, Minister of Foreign Affairs of Hungary, with Soviet views on the response to the note from Yugoslavia; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Gromyko re the Yugoslav note that doubted the reliability of published accounts of the court trial of I. Nagy and his group, with the recommendation of the USSR Ministry of Foreign Affairs as to a response; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft instructions to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary; message (sent via high frequency line, translated into Russian) from V. Astafiev, Soviet Chargé d'Affaires ad Interim to Hungary, with the text of the verbal note from the Yugoslav Embassy in Hungary denouncing violation of the agreement not to prosecute I. Nagy and his group; ciphered telegram from V. Astafiev reporting the reaction of the Hungarian population to the judicial sentence imposed on I. Nagy and his group, protests from Great Britain and Switzerland, and demonstrations of Hungarian émigrés at Hungarian embassies, 1958 June-July (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 77)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium approving, with amendments, directives to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary; the directives (two copies, differently formatted), directing that the ambassador visit Sik, Minister of Foreign Affairs of Hungary, and transmit to him a message that the draft note from Hungarian comrades had been approved by the TsK KPSS Presidium; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuznetsov, First Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs; resolution of the TsK KPSS approving a draft directive to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary; directive to the Soviet ambassador to Hungary, with Soviet amendments to the draft note of the Hungarian government to Yugoslavia to be transmitted to Sik; verbal note (translated into Russian) from Hungary to Yugoslavia, 1958 July (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 78)
    - Confidentiality agreement signed by I. Nagy as an agent of the 2nd Department of the United Main Political Directorate (OGPU) of the Council of People's Commissars, 1930 September (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 79)
    - Statement on the activity of the People's Commissariat of Internal Affairs (NKVD) agent I. Nagy ("Volodia") resulting in the arrest and trial of a counterrevolutionary group of Hungarian émigrés; two identical reports to V. Karutskii, Deputy Chief of the 4th Department of the NKVD Main Directorate on National Security, from Altman, Chief of the 2nd Division of the 4th Department of the Main Directorate on National Security, re the arrest and release of I. Nagy, 1938 March (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 80)
    - Statement on the biography and activity of the NKVD agent "Volodia," with cover letter to G. Malenkov from V. Merkulov, Deputy People's Commissar of Internal Affairs, submitting the statement about "Vladimir Iosifovich" Nagy, 1940 June (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 81)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kriuchkov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), re release to the Hungarian government (to oppose the campaign for Nagy's rehabilitation) of archival documents revealing the activity of I. Nagy as an NKVD agent, 1989 June (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 82)
    - Cover page to the letter of January 10, 1957, to the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia (CC LCY) from the TsK KPSS and the letter to the TsK KPSS from the CC LCY of February 7, 1957; resolution of the TsK KPSS approving the letter to the CC LCY from the TsK KPSS; the letter to the CC LCY from the TsK KPSS, criticizing the Yugoslav position toward the events in Hungary and its interference in the internal affairs of other countries and communist parties, its military cooperation with the United States, and Yugoslav opposition to the Soviet socialist system introduced in Yugoslavia, 1957 January-February (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 83)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from J. Tito in the name of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia (CC LCY), reporting that the letters that the LCY and the KPSS had exchanged were presented at the Plenum of the CC LCY, and submitting a letter to the TsK KPSS from the Plenum of the CC LCY; the letter denouncing Soviet allegations re the Yugoslav position toward I. Nagy and the activity of the Kádár government, criticizing the TsK KPSS position toward the Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party and toward Yugoslavia, asserting the rights of the LCY to have its own position toward the development of socialist countries and the Soviet socialist system, and complaining of intelligence and other hostile activity of Albania, Bulgaria, and Czechoslovakia in Yugoslavia, 1957 February (Opis 45, Reel 1.1004, File 84)
  - Opis 46
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from I. Serbin, Chief of the Department of Defense Industry, recommending that V. Yemelianov, Corresponding Member of the USSR Academy of Sciences, reject a prize from the Atoms for Peace Rockfeller Foundation (two copies); memorandum to the TsK KPSS from E. Slavskii, Minister of Medium Machine Building Industry; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from M. Keldysh, President of the USSR Academy of Sciences, and IA. Peive, Chief Academic Secretary of the Presidium of the USSR Academy of Sciences, requesting that the TsK KPSS authorize Yemelianov to receive the Prize; letter (translated into Russian) to Yemelianov from G. Killian, Jr., Chairman of the Atoms for Peace Foundation; Yemelianov's personal data, 1966 July-August (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 1)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from D. Shevliagin, Chief of the Department of Information, proposing measures to oppose the conclusions drawn in New Trends in Soviet Economics, published in five volumes by the Economic Commission of the US Congress, 1966 August (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 2)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Zaichikov, First Deputy Chairman of the Board of the News Publishing Agency (Agenstvo Pechati Novosti - APN), supported by D. Shevliagin, Chief of the Department of Information, requesting that the TsK KPSS approve the creation, in cooperation with the ABC American television network, of a television program about a worker from the Rostov-on-Don plant, 1966 August; 1966 September (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 3)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi and V. Kuznetsov re the accidental crossing of the Soviet state border by the American citizen T. Dowson(?), member of the Peace Corps in Iran, 1966 September (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 4)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from B. Burkov, Chairman of the Board of the News Publishing Agency (Agenstvo Pechati Novosti - APN), supported by D. Shevliagin, Chief of the Department of Information, requesting that the TsK KPSS authorize the broadcast by an American company of a program on Vietnam based on Soviet documents, with commentaries by G. Borovik, Chief of the APN station in the United States, 1967 March (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 5)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 6)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Ulianovskii, Deputy Chief of the International Department, and I. Makarov, Deputy Chief of the Department of Science and Educational Institutions, supporting the request from G. Hall, Secretary General of the National Committee of the Communist Party USA (N.C. CPUSA), to award the title of Honorable Doctor of Historical Science of Moscow State University (MGU) to J. Jackson, member of the N.C. CPUSA; memorandum (translated into Russian) to the TsK KPSS from G. Hall; the same memorandum in English, 1969 September-October (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 7)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), proposing measures to denounce S. Allilueva's book Only One Year (Tolko odin god) containing anti-Lenin and anti-Soviet propaganda, 1969 November (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 8)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov and A. Gromyko re measures to use the stay of four US Navy servicemen (who deserted from the Vietnam war) for propaganda purposes; three additional copies of the first page of the memorandum, each signed by a TsK secretary; report signed by G. Shumeiko, Head of a Sector of the International Department, on the discussion that took place in his Department re the servicemen's stay in the Soviet Union, 1967 November (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 9)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Ulianovskii, Deputy Chief of the International Department, and N. Petrovichev, Deputy Chief of the Department of Organizational and Party Work, re assisting the Student Union of East Pakistan in celebration of V. Lenin's 100th anniversary; personal data of G. Ptitsyn (head of the delegation to East Pakistan) and of S. Serebrianyi and V. Kozlov (members of the same delegation); recommendation provided for Ptitsyn by A. Danilov, Secretary of the VLKSM (All-Union Young Communists League) Committee of Omskaia oblast; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from E. Tiazhelnikov, Secretary of the VLKSM Central Committee; list of supplies to be delivered to the Student Union of East Pakistan; statement signed by G. Shumeiko, Chief of the International Department, about the Student Union of East Pakistan, 1969 September; 1970 March (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 10)
    - Copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a draft letter to be sent to KPSS organizations re distribution of America magazine in the Soviet Union; the draft letter accompanied by a cover letter to the TsK KPSS from F. Konstantinov, Chief of the Department of Propaganda and Agitation of the TsK KPSS Bureau for the Union Republics, 1956 July-August (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 11)
    - Copy of the extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving the text of a note to the commandant of the US sector of Berlin from the commandant of the Soviet sector re provocative actions of American authorities toward the Soviet writer and defector A. Cheishvili, and directing that the Committee for State Security (KGB) and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs take all possible steps to clarify the circumstances of Cheishvili's "kidnapping" and to bring him back from West Germany; the draft note to General Hamlet(?); memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Mukhitdinov, A. Gromyko, and K. Lunev, with Cheishvili's biographical data and description of the circumstances under which he defected; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; report about Cheishvili and the officials who recommended him for a business trip to East Germany and authorized his trip, 1958 December (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 12)
    - Copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat appointing B. Ponomarev, L. Ilichev, and G. A. Zhukov to work out proposals with respect to a memorandum from the writer B. Polevoi; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from B. Ponomarev, Chief of the International Department, proposing measures to facilitate rapprochement of the Soviet and American peoples as discussed in the Polevoi memorandum; summary of Polevoi's memorandum, signed by N. Mostovets, Head of a Sector of the International Department; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium; the memorandum to N. Khrushchev from B. Polevoi; resolution and extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Commission for Ideology, Culture, and International Party Relations, 1958 May; 1958 November-December (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 13)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from L. Ilichev, Chief of the Department of Propaganda and Agitation of the TsK KPSS Bureau for the Union Republics, and G. Kazakov, Head of a Sector of the same department, re measures to be taken to actively oppose hostile propaganda broadcasts to the Soviet population; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Sergiichuk, Minister of Communications, proposing an improvement in distribution of broadcasting equipment to oppose hostile radio propaganda; statement from V. Snastin, Deputy Chief of the Department of Propaganda and Agitation of the TsK KPSS Bureau for the Union Republics, and G. Kazakov approving measures proposed by Sergiichuk; report to the TsK KPSS from M. Yegorov, Chief of the Technical Directorate of the State Committee for Radio and Television (Gosteleradio), and V. Kuzmin, Chief Engineer of the Main Radio Directorate of the Ministry of Communications, re introduction of special programs for eastern regions of the Soviet Union; report to the TsK KPSS Bureau for the RSFSR from A. Kosulnikov, Deputy Chief of the Department of Propaganda and Agitation of the TsK KPSS Bureau for the RSFSR, re broadcasting to Magadankaia oblast; memorandum to the TsK KPSS Bureau for the RSFSR from P. Afanasiev, Secretary of the KPSS Committee of Magadankaia oblast; 14 memoranda to the TsK KPSS: from A. Miglinik, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Latvia, from L. Mokerov, Secretary of the KPSS Committee of Kirovskaia oblast, from I. Senkin, Secretary of the Karelia KPSS Committee, from I. Kirienko, Secretary of the KPSS Committee of Permskaia oblast, from KH. Sairanov, Secretary of the KPSS Committee of Bashkiria, from the Secretary of the Central Committee of the Uzbek Communist Party (signature is illegible), from P. Tashliev, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Turkmenistan, from V. Agkantsev, Secretary of the North Ossetian KPSS Committee, from L. Lentsman, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Estonia, from N. Rocher, Secretary of the Komi KPSS Committee, from N. Gadzhiev, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Azerbaijan, from M. Belenov, Chief of the Propaganda and Agitation Department of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Kazakhstan, from K. Dzharkimbekov, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Kazakhstan, and from T. Uldzhabaev, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Tadzhikistan, re implementation of the TsK KPSS resolution On Measures for Active Opposition to Hostile Radio Propaganda; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Romanov, Deputy Chief of the Department of Propaganda and Agitation of the TsK KPSS Bureau for the Union Republics, and G. Kazakov; report to the TsK KPSS from A. Kaftanov, Chairman of the State Committee for Radio and Television (Gosteleradio); program of Soviet broadcasting to be aired simultaneously with hostile (foreign) radio propaganda; resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat, 1960 July - 1961 January (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 14)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Rudenko and P. Ivashutin re the arrest of, and possible penalty for M. Kaminskii, American tourist, charged with intelligence activity against the Soviet Union (according to a resolution of the TsK KPSS); decree of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet on the expulsion from the Soviet Union of M. Kaminskii, sentenced to a seven-year prison term; copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat, 1960 September (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 15)
    - Copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a request from W. Foster, Honorary Chairman of the National Committee of the Communist Party USA, to provide financial assistance to his daughter S. Kolko; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Tereshkin, Deputy Chief of the International Department, 1961 July (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 16)
    - Copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a request from the Communist Party USA (CPUSA) that the KPSS arrange the distribution in the Soviet Union of The Worker Midweek newspaper, supplement to The Worker newspaper (CPUSA) in the Soviet Union; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Yegorov, Deputy Chief of the Department of Propaganda and Agitation of the TsK KPSS Bureau for the Union Republics, and V. Korionov, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Sazhin, Chief of the Main Directorate for All-Union Publishing (Soiuzpechat); memorandum to the TsK KPSS from D. Robinson (Distribution Department of The Worker; statement signed by A. A. Pavlov, Deputy Chairman of the Mezhdunarodnaia kniga (International Book) All-Union Association, with information about The Worker Midweek and its subscription price; cover letter to the TsK KPSS from Pavlov, accompanying a sample of The Worker Midweek, 1961 October-December (Opis 46, Reel 1.1005, File 17)